[SPEAKER_01]: I wanted to speak about the issue of the hindrance of sloth and torpor.
[SPEAKER_01]: Tīna-mīda is the Pali.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I like to call it just laziness.
[SPEAKER_01]: And in the suttas, there's a simile for this kind of state.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha says, suppose there is a bowl of water covered with water plants and algae.
[SPEAKER_01]: A man with good eyesight, standing on the bank, would not see his own facial reflection as it really is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, too, when a monk dwells with a mind overcome by sloth and torpor, he does not understand what is for his own welfare, for the welfare of others, or for the welfare of both.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's a
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a covering.
[SPEAKER_01]: It makes things unclear.
[SPEAKER_00]: If your mind is clouded, indolent, lazy, no perspective is because you made it so directly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even more so than if you were, say, you know, have a tendency towards desire too much or tendency towards ill will.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's also a result of your actions, but it kind of gets its own momentum.
[SPEAKER_00]: But with this, like, the momentum is always directly sustained, the momentum of your indolence, if you could even call it momentum, through you choosing to not go against it, to not really just, like, pull yourself out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's always practically manifested through, yeah,
[SPEAKER_00]: Choosing out of a preference to, say, not think about certain things because, oh, they're a bit uncomfortable, or I can't deal with that now, or I'll address that later, procrastinate, you could get up when you wake up, oh, that's just... that would be a bit uncomfortable, so I shall rather just indulge in this completely unnecessary, slimy, sticky, heavy comfort that I'm currently in.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's always by that immediate choice that's how you're maintaining that very kind of sticky, weighty state of mind that then it feels like, oh, I can't break out of this.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just get up and go for a long walk.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just gonna feel... you have no motivation to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have no reason to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're sleepy.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to rest.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just, no, I'll just go out and walk.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's kind of... in a way, it's that simple.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it would go against the entire grain of your mind there and then.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you just... there's... you're trying to just, yeah, stay with comfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't want to... Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's not even... and again, like, see, it can go that far.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, if you're reaching, like, the levels of, like, chronic depression and so on, you're not even staying with the comfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's uncomfortable already.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's uncomfortable.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the thought of kind of moving, or at least exerting some, going against some degree of inertia, feels even worse.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, because what you are currently in is less uncomfortable than the projected idea of going against this inertia, that's why I'll just stay with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's uncomfortable.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not... it's far from being agreeable and pleasant at that point.
[SPEAKER_01]: So if, you know, one is laying around
[SPEAKER_01]: After you've... you have a rest and you wake up, you want to... and there's a tendency to just stay in bed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, to linger.
[SPEAKER_01]: I just can't stay here a little bit longer and let... just go with the mind's thoughts here and there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And... but then... okay, I'm just get up, go for a walk, as you say, but...
[SPEAKER_01]: Is that not now just kind of reaction, like a... the wrong thing to do, rather than... Well, no, it's a reaction to the right extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if things are too loose, you need to react towards tightening.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not for its own sake, but for the sake of tightening that which was too loose.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, like, if I just had to stay in bed and just say, well, now I'm just going to just be awake... You're not.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's already... like, if you try to stay in bed, because you don't really want to stay in bed, or you're not that pressured to stay in bed, but for whatever reason you choose to stay in bed, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you're clearly staying in bed, because getting out of the bed, the inertia that that kind of exhibits, is just, ah, I don't want to bother with that now, then whatever you do on account of staying in bed will be done on account of already made compromise.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not about, oh, I will start restricting my sleep and set up the alarm to wake me up in the middle of the night and then I must force myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's when that choice presents itself to either go with the inertia, path of less resistance,
[SPEAKER_00]: Or go against it?
[SPEAKER_00]: What do you choose?
[SPEAKER_00]: And that choice will present... you don't have to manufacture it or force it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're gonna have ample opportunity to exercise the right choice when it comes to the hindrances, just on account of basic restraint and the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you don't need to go to the extremes and start, as I said, tormenting or depriving yourself of sleep to get to this point.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: These little, as I said, little paths of less resistance here.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when you know, when you're aware, what do you choose?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what matters.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, after a hard day's work, or working hard in whatever, on some project, and you generally are tired, then there's a choice, maybe at the end of the day, you get back and you rest.
[SPEAKER_01]: I just want to zone out, you know, I want to just kind of drift into nonsense, you know, even just watching things on the internet just drift away and kind of forget about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's kind of... that's going with the laziness.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's going with the... the hindrance, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, you need to see where the... where the line between factual need of rest and indolence is crossed, where that line is crossed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you come back from... like, if you're genuinely tired, which obviously you would be sooner or later, yeah, one thing is to then have the rest that you actually need, and another thing is to turn that rest
[SPEAKER_00]: into exactly like mindless, completely like loss of context, loss of perspective, entertainment, indulgence, which obviously for people is kind of became synonymous with rest.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, even if they come home and start resting,
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, factually resting, unless they enter into the, that, as I said, half-asleep state of entertainment and laziness, they won't feel like they rested.
[SPEAKER_00]: But all the factually... No, you have rested.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, resting means just sitting down, calming down, not working, not distracting yourself either.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the distraction has become synonymous with rest, so that needs to be unlearned.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, initially, when you don't give in to distraction, it will feel like you haven't rested.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not so.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are actually having rest.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have rested, but just your mind hasn't got what it wants, so it's going to feel a bit restless on account of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's a different thing to have a restless mind and to factually need actually just to rest because you were tired.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's... you can sit down and relax physically.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're off actually getting rest.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not doing anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Go to sleep, rest.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not letting... not even watching things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, your eyes are at rest as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just everything's at rest.
[SPEAKER_01]: But your mind is not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have to unlearn the identification, the gratuitous identification of the factual rest with entertainment and mindlessness.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you let your mind disappear in the content or whatever, that's not resting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how do you get the mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, by saying no to the extent of entertainment and mindless... mindless wandering and distraction and indolence.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then it starts going...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, saying no to those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to rest.
[SPEAKER_00]: Go lay down.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, while you're laying down, you want to watch something, listen something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, say no to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, but that will disturb the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, the mind might be disturbed initially until it unlearns the bad habits.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you are getting the rest that you physically need.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have to kind of go through a certain amount of withdrawal from that dependence on those mindless activities.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the mind is already disturbed.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, and then you saying no to its need for entertainment, it's still agitated, but eventually
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's agitated, but it's not... it won't be tired.
[SPEAKER_00]: Initially, as I said, distraction is the only way to get rid of tiredness, because it implies some degree of factual resting.
[SPEAKER_00]: But my point is that factual resting does not require you to go as far as the distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's what a person needs to discern through practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can theorize and ponder about it all you want,
[SPEAKER_00]: But the fact is, basically, you actually have to start doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to start going against that inertia when it presents itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Enduring it, not acting out of it, on those levels of conscious choices, when they're clearly outlined there, when you know what you're choosing, when you know what you're doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I was thinking that another relaxation should result in feeling rested at the end of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you're doing something as a relaxation and you're feeling even more worse, more tired, that didn't quite work.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your sensuality, though that's used as a relaxation technique, you don't feel rested and light after it, burden-free, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: The weight has been lifted.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's even worse.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, definitely.